All right, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is מד, Mem
Dalet, four four.
We pick up on the middle of מג עמוד ב. Mem Gimmel
Amud Bet. The two dots,
about exactly halfway down, about four lines after the new גמרא Gemara
began, and the משנה Mishna deals with the question about who collects
the girl's כתובה. ksuva. So if she's divorced from אירוסין, erusin, first
of all there's an assumption that there is a כתובה ksuva payout
already at אירוסין, erusin, we'll get the גמרא Gemara will discuss that
briefly and it'll be a larger discussion later. And then the father
gets it because the father's still in control of her through אירוסין,
erusin, and that he can even remarry her after a divorce from
אירוסין. erusin. But if it's after נישואין, nisuin, she gets it, except
we have the position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says actually
after the first נישואין nisuin the father gets it if the father
married her off when she was a קטנה. ksana. So that's what
the גמרא Gemara turns its attention to. So let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda
omer, we are four lines, one, two, four lines under where the
big bold גמרא Gemara is, smack in the middle of the page.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, הראשונה של אב. harishona shel av.
So the payment of the first כתובה ksuva goes to the father
again in a case where the father married her off when she
was a קטנה. ksana. So the גמרא Gemara says: מאי טעמא דרבי
יהודה? Mai taama d'Rabbi Yehuda? What's his reasoning? רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי
תרווייהו, Rabba v'Rav Yosef d'amri tarvaihu, הואיל ומשעת אירוסין זכה בהן האב.
hoil umishaat erusin zachah bahen ha-av. Because he says, look, the first
part of the משנה Mishna told you if she got divorced from
אירוסין, erusin, the father would collect because she's still under his control.
So when the כתובה ksuva obligations began, they began at אירוסין, erusin,
and who are they payable to at the time of אירוסין? erusin?
The father. So now that she goes ahead and she goes to
the חופה, chuppah, the כתובה ksuva doesn't change from being payable to
the father. Okay, so that's his argument, right? If she was divorced
from אירוסין, erusin, he would collect it. So even if she gets
through to נישואין, nisuin, the כתובה ksuva obligations already began at the
time of אירוסין, erusin, and they began to the father. So they
remain payable to the father even after נישואין. nisuin. It's a pretty
reasonable position. Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about this.
מתיב רבא. Masiv Rava. רבא Rava asks from the following ברייתא: braita:
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, הראשונה של אב. harishona shel av.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says the payment of the first כתובה ksuva
even from נישואין nisuin goes to the father again if he married
her off as a קטנה ksana during אירוסין. erusin. ומודה רבי יהודה,
U'modeh Rabbi Yehuda, but רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would concede the following
case: במארס את בתו כשהיא קטנה, B'm'ares et bito k'she-hi ksana, he
did אירוסין erusin when she was a minor, ובגרה, u'bagrah, but before
the נישואין nisuin she became an adult, she hit puberty, ואחר כך
נישאת, v'achar kach nisat, and then she had נישואין, nisuin, שאין לאביה
רשות בה. she-ein l'aviha reshut bah. At that time, by the time
of נישואין, nisuin, she was out of the control of the father.
So you understand what happened? Right, here's the father, right, and here's
his daughter, okay,
so he marries her off, right, and this is אירוסין, erusin, okay.
So at this stage, she's under his control, and the כתובה ksuva
is payable, right, if she were to get divorced right now, she
would get a כתובה ksuva and he would get it, okay. So
then,
so if she becomes now a בוגרת, bogeret, so then the father
is out of the picture, okay.
So now that she's a בוגרת, bogeret, father's out of the picture,
and now here she is standing under the חופה chuppah with her
חתן, chosson, and here they're under the חופה, chuppah, okay, and they
have and they have their נישואין. nisuin. Now, okay, yes, exactly. So,
okay, here's the argument. The argument is one minute. If you think
according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that the reason he collects after
נישואין, nisuin, the father, from the first marriage is because at the
time of אירוסין erusin there was already a כתובה ksuva obligation, and
as we learned, everybody would agree that if she would get divorced
at the time of אירוסין, erusin, the כתובה ksuva would be payable
to the father. So if you're basically saying so he remains the
payee of the כתובה ksuva even after the time of נישואין nisuin
because he began to be the payee here, it shouldn't matter that
she's a בוגרת bogeret at this stage. He was the payee, he
remains to be the payee, right? So you're saying well, it doesn't
matter that here she goes out of his control, it started as
he was the payee, that doesn't change. So then it shouldn't matter
that she's gone out of his control here either. The כתובה ksuva
should still be payable to the father. So why does רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda agree in this case that the כתובה ksuva actually is
now payable to her? That's the question.
Yes, אירוסין erusin and חופה, chuppah, no? חופה chuppah changes her status
even if she were a נערה. naarah.
Okay,
so you could say that, that there's maybe a different degree of
change of status. What the גמרא Gemara is going to say is
you know what happens right before the כתובה? ksuva? Here it's the
כתובה ksuva obligation because it's a תקנת חכמים, takanas chachamim, תקנת, takanas,
you know, חז"ל Chazal that there's כתובה ksuva obligations even without it
being written. But what happens right before the חופה chuppah is that
the כתובה ksuva gets written. You actually write a כתובה ksuva and
that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. So let's take
a look at that answer, okay. the answer obligations because it's a
תקנת חכמים, takanas chachamim, תקנת, takanas, you know חז״ל Chazal that there's
כתובה kesubah obligations even without it being written. But what happens right
before the חופה chuppah is that the כתובה kesubah gets written. You
actually write a כתובה, kesubah, and that's what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say. So let's take a look at that answer, okay?
So the גמרא's Gemara answer is: the answer is, so הכא נמי,
hacha nami, הכא נמי דשדי לה בירושת אבא אמאי, hacha nami deshadi
lah biyirushas abba amai,
why does he concede this case? הכא נמי לימא, hacha nami leima,
here too let us say, הואיל ומשעת אירוסין זכה בה אב, hoil
umishas eirusin zachah bah av, the father already has rights to it.
So אלא אי איתמר הכי איתמר, ella i itmar hachi itmar, here's
how Rabbi Yehuda's position was explained. רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו, Rabbah
verav Yosef deamri tarvaihu, they both say, הואיל וברשותו נכתבין. hoil ubireshuso
nichtavin.
Okay, since it's written under his control. So this is scenario number
one of בוגרת. bogeret. Scenario number two is she's not a בוגרת
bogeret while she's still a קטנה, ketanah, that's already when she's having
the חופה. chuppah. Okay?
So that's scenario number two. And the כתובה kesubah is written here.
So here's the difference. The difference is it's not because he remains
to be the payee and it doesn't matter what happens afterwards. No,
actually when the כתובה kesubah gets written, it redefines the obligation. Here's
the difference. Here when the כתובה kesubah is written, right,
here she's a קטנה. ketanah. Here when the כתובה kesubah is written,
it's being written under his auspices. Right? He leaves his control at
the time of נישואין. nissuin. But the כתובה kesubah is written an
hour before at the טיש. tish. Okay? It's written right before he
leaves his control. So this creates the new obligations as opposed to
the unwritten obligations. The written obligations are the new ones. In this
scenario, those obligations are created while she's still under his control before
she stands under the חופה. chuppah. And therefore the first כתובה, kesubah,
if it's when she's a קטנה, ketanah, is written while she's a
קטנה, ketanah, and therefore he becomes the payee because it's written under
his control, the father. In this scenario, she becomes emancipated first, and
then the new כתובה kesubah obligations created by the writing of the
כתובה kesubah occur once she's her own person. So it's not because
of this, the unwritten obligations, which are true, do exist. The writing
of the כתובה kesubah creates new obligations. But Rabbi Yehuda would say
if it's being written while she's a קטנה, ketanah, then that
then he becomes the payee. If it's written while she's a גדולה,
gedolah, he does not. Yes.
What's the כתובה kesubah for? Or in return for what does she
get the כתובה? kesubah?
Well,
the specific thing we're talking about is the עיקר כתובה, ikkar kesubah,
the 200 זוז zuz or whatever. And she doesn't get it in
return for, I mean, she gets it to protect her interest. She
gets it in case they ever get divorced or widowed, that there'll
be money to support her.
Like for her ongoing support or benefit.
Well, the ongoing support in terms of like the פרנסה parnasah that
he provides for the food and the lodge and whatever, that's not
what we're talking about. That's called תנאי כתובה. tenai kesubah. We dealt
with that yesterday about like if she's being supported by the estate,
that's not what we're talking about. We're talking about the כתובה kesubah
when it's payable, the 200 זוז. zuz. And that's really to serve
to protect her in a case of divorce or widowhood.
But but you're saying it's essentially to ensure that this will likely
or you know even possibly take place in the future when she
is... Right. Right.
Even though it's written while she's under his control, the point of
it is to be payable many years from now when she's her
own person. And to even state your question sharper, which is if
the whole point is to protect her interest, what good does it
do to be payable to the father? Right, it should be payable
to her. Right. So yeah, it's very bizarre. There's no like good
instead of you know sort of social purpose that's being served, you
know, or whatever by being having it payable to the father. What?
Even from a contractual purpose it's understood that let's say a certain
portion of it goes to the father because once she gets divorced
or... Right. Right. Right.
So but you
know, if she's eleven and a half, you could say that. Let's
say she has the נישואין nissuin at at the ripe old age
of four. Right.
So I mean what Rabbi Yehuda would be, I mean, it's a
a word I use often, but he would be like a somewhat
of a formalist. He says, look, right now she's under the father's
control. So we define the obligation in terms of who is the
person that can be pay you know in this right now that
it would be payable to. So, you know, so if
one later whatever things change, we can only you know we can
only deal with the realities we have. Some type of an idea
like that. But I agree, it's crazy. Because obviously the whole point
is that she's going to be left, you know, why she needs
the כתובה kesubah is after the divorce or death, the father won't
take her back in. She's going to be on her own and
she's going to need it. So yeah, it is very strange. Dovie.
Is to me is it is it accurate to say that in
the second scenario really the כתובה kesubah should be read like בי
אבויה, bi avuhah, right? In other words בי אבויה's bi avuhah got
that legal force...
Yeah,
that could be. But the בי אבויה bi avuhah has to also
do of where the dowry is coming from. But yes, that that
is that different... Right. Yeah. All right.
So now so that's Rabbi Yehuda's argument, okay? So the basic point
is that when the כתובה kesubah is written, it recreates the obligations.
That seems to be... agreed even by רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, that
the writing of it before the נשואין nisu'in recreates, but he says,
okay, but when's the נשואין nisu'in taking place? If she's still a
קטנה, ketannah, then those obligations are deferred to the father. To now
understanding that the writing of the כתובה ketubah recreates obligations, the גמרא'ס
Gemara's going to have an interesting question. Let's take a look at
the גמרא'ס Gemara's question. It says like this.
ומגבי מאימת גביא. U-migba mei-eimat gavya. When is the כתובה ketubah collected
from? So again, assuming that as the משנה Mishnah assumes, that the
כתובה'ס ketubah's payable already from אירוסין. erusin.
So when if it went from אירוסין erusin to נשואין nisu'in and
the כתובה ketubah created, was, the writing of the כתובה ketubah recreated
the obligations, can you collect with liens, do the liens exist from
the time of the אירוסין? erusin? Now everybody get the scenario. Meaning
the אירוסין erusin occurred in the year 2010. She got the, the
חופה chuppah was in the year 2015. Okay, and that's when we
wrote the כתובה. ketubah. If she had gotten divorced between 2010 and
2015 she'd collect her כתובה. ketubah. She כתובה'ס ketubah's payable even from
the אירוסין. erusin. But now she got her the חופה chuppah and
the rewriting of the כתובה ketubah in 2015. And now in 2030
she's coming to collect. When does she have liens on the חתן'ס
choson's estate? As of 2015 or as of 2010? Because you understand
the question, right? Because since we've implicitly said that the writing of
the כתובה ketubah recreates the obligations, so the payee can change, right?
What about the liens? Do the liens survive from the time of
the אירוסין erusin and continue through so she can collect? You understand
what I mean by liens, right? The חתן choson had land, had
real estate, he sold it between 2010 and 2015. Comes 2030 he
doesn't have any cash to pay the כתובה. ketubah. Can she collect
from the property he sold, you know, at from to
between 2010 and 2015? Does her lien since the כתובה ketubah obligations
began in 2010, do the liens continue from them? Or since they
were, you know, they were recreated in 2015 at the time of
the חופה, chuppah, maybe that's when the liens exist. Refinance. Okay, yeah,
there you go. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says ומגבי מאימת גביא.
U-migba mei-eimat gavya. When can she from what date can she collect,
you know, does she have liens on the estate?
A lien could usually be collected from the לקוחות, lekuchos, right?
That's the whole point of the lien. Exactly. No, any estate any
property he has under his control whether cattle or real estate, she
can collect from. The point of a lien is that you collect
it even from even when someone else bought it. Well, you know,
that right now it's true. Exactly, you have to do a title
search, which is why there are only liens when there are when
it's a שטר, shtar, when it's written down, when it's when it's
a matter of record. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ומגבי מאימת
גביא. U-migba mei-eimat gavya. אמר רב הונא: Amar Rav Huna: מנה מאתיים
מן האירוסין. Manah masayim min ha-erusin. So the core כתובה ketubah because
the core כתובה ketubah is what's obligated even when it isn't written,
and that's exists from the אירוסין. erusin. So those liens continue from
the time of the
אירוסין. erusin. התוספת Ha-tosefet but any additional amount that he wanted to
add which is something that really would only be added when the
כתובה ketubah was written and would only be added at the time
of נשואין, nisu'in, that's מן הנשואין. min ha-nisu'in. That's from the נשואין.
nisu'in. So basically what he is saying is the obligation that existed
from אירוסין erusin the liens continue. Even though רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
might be saying even though we might be saying somehow that they
get rewritten, it gets redefined at that time and it allows it
to be an obligation to the daughter rather than to the father,
whatever it might be, nevertheless the liens of the debt that existed
earlier continue continue.
The only thing that is new is the thing that's added at
the time of the נשואין nisu'in is the תוספת. tosefet. That's what
he says. ורב אסי: Ve-Rav Assi: אמר
רב אסי Amar Rav Assi says: אחד זה ואחד זה מן הנשואין.
Echad zeh ve-echad zeh min ha-nisu'in. No, which is maybe the more
natural thing to say once we made this assertion we just did,
that since it it changes from being payable to the father to
payable to the daughter, right? So therefore that the whole thing is
redefined at the time of the נשואין nisu'in and therefore all of
the liens only exist from the time of the נשואין nisu'in on.
Okay, so that's the next I would say the natural thing to
say given what we had prefaced it with. So the גמרא Gemara
says ומי אמר רב הונא הכי U-mi amar Rav Huna hachi? Now
does רב הונא Rav Huna really say that you split between the
core כתובה ketubah which exists from earlier and the new one which
is only from now, which is only from the נשואין? nisu'in? והאמר
ואיתמר Ve-ha-amar ve-itmar it was talked: הוציאה עליו שתי כתובות. Hotzi'ah alav
shetei ketubos. Let's say when they got divorced and she says actually
I have two כתובות ketubos that had been written for her, okay,
from this guy, and there's no question like neither's a forgery or
whatever. We'll see why he would have written two in a minute,
but he wrote two
כתובות. ketubos. Let's take a look. אחת של מאתיים ואחת של שלוש
מאות. Achas shel masayim ve-achas shel shelosh mei'os. One is dated, you
know, 2015 for 200 זוז zuz and one is dated 2017 for
300 זוז. zuz. Okay,
so גובה מזמן שני. govah mi-zman sheini. So she can so what
I'm sorry did I skip a line? ואמר רב הונא: Ve-amar Rav
Huna: באה לגבות מאתיים. Ba'ah ligvos masayim. If she wants to collect
the 200 זוז zuz one which has an earlier date, גובה מזמן
ראשון. govah mi-zman rishon. Fine, she's entitled to even use it with
liens against property. property that he had under his control even from
the earlier date 2015. So that's a lesser amount, but the liens,
but it was an earlier date, so the liens started earlier, right?
And therefore she can get more, she has more access to more,
to more, to more of his, of his, of the land that
he might have sold. So
גובה מזמן ראשון. gove mi'zman rishon. שלוש מאות, Shalosh me'os, if she
wants to collect the 300 one, fine, she can do that, but
the liens are later. גובה מזמן שני. gove mi'zman sheni. The liens
are later.
Now, why doesn't she give them 200 from one time?
So that's the גמרא's Gemara question. The גמרא Gemara understands that logically
if you have a 200 with an earlier date and a 300
with a later date, conceptually the גמרא Gemara understands what's happened is
that he's basically said I'm going to add an extra 100 on
to your כתובה. ketubah. So if that's true the גמרא Gemara says
given רב הונא Rav Huna she should be entitled to use the
300 כתובה ketubah to collect, collect 200 of it from the earlier
date and 100 from the later date since he's in general willing
to split in this case of two כתובות ketubahs he should logically
be willing to split as well because isn't that what's happening with
the 300, it's just adding an extra 100 to the pre-existing debt.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. ואי איתא, V'i issa,
if what you're saying רב הונא Rav Huna is correct, how are
you this, this is also a statement of רב הונא, Rav Huna,
how are you consistent? תיגבי מאתיים מזמן ראשון ומאה מזמן שני. Tigvi
masayim mi'zman rishon u'me'ah mi'zman sheni. The 200 should be from the
earlier date and the extra 100 should be from the new date.
All right, so that's the גמרא's Gemara question. Mike I always tell
you you could write the גמרא. Gemara. ולטעמיך, U'l'ta'ameich, the גמרא Gemara
says according to your logic, why don't you say תיגבי חמש מאות?
tigbi chamesh me'os? So why don't you collect 500? Why don't we
just say no it wasn't 200 plus 100, she had a 200
debt and he wanted to add 300 debt and he wanted to
make a total 500. Let's say that's what it means, okay, and
let her collect 500? תיגבי חמש
מאות כולהו, מאתיים מזמן ראשון ותלת מאה מזמן שני. Tigvi chamesh me'os
kulehu, masayim mi'zman rishon v'slas me'ah mi'zman sheni. אלא, Ella, so why
don't we say that? חמש מאות מאי טעמא לא גביא? Chamesh me'os
mai ta'ama lo gavia? Why do we not say that he wanted
to create a 500 debt? כיון, Keivan, well that's exactly what Michael
told you, you're writing the גמרא. Gemara. This is what the גמרא
Gemara says. כיון דלא כתב לה, Keivan d'lo kasav lah, since he
did not write in the second כתובה. ketubah. If he wanted to
have the second כתובה ketubah to be in addition, whether it was
200 plus 300 or whether it was 200 plus 100, there's language
he could have used that would have spelled out that the second
one was in addition to the first and here's what he could
have said. כיון דלא כתב לה, Keivan d'lo kasav lah, he did
not write the following: צביתי ואוספי ליה לך תלת מאה אמאתיים. Z'visi
v'osifis lach slas me'ah a'masayim. I have desired and I've added to
you
300 on the existing 200. I'm maintaining the validity of the first
one and I'm adding the second. He didn't say that. So because
he didn't say that we know he didn't mean 500. Okay.
הכי קאמר לה. Hachi ka'amar lah. So therefore since he didn't say
that what is he saying? He's not saying 500. What's he saying
by writing a 300 one? אי מזמן ראשון גבית, גבית מאתיים. Im
mi'zman rishon gavis, gavis masayim. He's basically saying I'm not doing this
in addition, I'm giving you another option. You have an option of
a 200 כתובה ketubah from an earlier date and you could use
that if you want. I'm giving you an option of a 300
כתובה ketubah from a later date. אי מזמן שני גבית, גבית תלת
מאה. Im mi'zman sheni gavis, gavis slas me'ah. If you want to
collect from the second time you can collect 300. So that's how
we read what the second כתובה ketubah means. Okay, it does not
mean 300 plus 200. Okay, but somehow we assume not. We assume
if you don't, I don't know why, you're right, like which one
should we assume is the default. Okay, but if you want to
increase the debt, right, then we're going to sort of read it
300 plus 200, we're not going to say that. We're going to
see these as alternatives.
Okay, wait, wait let's just finish the argument. Hold on. So that's
why we don't say 500. So similarly you wanted to read the
300 as saying the original 200 plus 100. No, if that's what
it meant he should have said it. הכא נמי, היינו טעמא דלא
גביא. Hacha nami, hainu ta'ama d'lo gavia. Here's the reason why we
don't read the 300 as the original 200 plus 100 and use
the original 200 from the earlier date. Mid top of מ"ד ע"ד.
mem daled amud daled. מדלא כתב לה, Mi'd'lo kasav lah, because if
that's what he had wanted he would have written the following: אוספי
ליה לך מאה אמאתיים. Osifis lach me'ah a'masayim. So I am adding
to you 100 on the 200. So since he didn't write that,
right, he didn't explain that 300 meant the original thing plus 100.
So again we will interpret these things they are separate documents. In
a way this is the most natural thing to do. They're separate
and competing documents. Pick one. That's how we're interpreting them. Don't read
them as A plus B. Don't read them as B is A
plus something. No they're separate and competing documents you got to pick
one. אחולי אחליה לשעבודה קמא Acholi achlei l'shibuda kama and therefore if
you want to use the later one you have to waive the
first שעבוד shibud and this is a totally new obligation in 300.
So what it is saying is this is no question. You say
why is the 300 not the early 200 plus 100 and let
him split when she collects from and the answer is because the
document doesn't say it. If we have competing documents we're going to
interpret them as competing documents. She has the right to pick one
but we're not going to read them as adding on to one
another or reinterpreting one another and therefore that's that case. But in
a normal case of a כתובה ketubah where at the אירוסין erusin
it starts with a base obligation of 200 and when he comes
to write it he explicitly is saying I am adding a תוספת
tosefes of X amount on the base
obligation, that's. we would see it as a layered obligation. The earlier
200 begins from the time of אירוסין, Erusin, the additional amount begins
from the time of נישואין. Nisuin.
Okay, how would you translate אחולי אחיל צלי שיעבודא גמנא? achuli achil
tzel she'abuda gamna?
You said that she has basically waived her earlier lien. If
she chooses to use the second one, then she's implicitly, maybe a
better word than waive is
sort of sacrifice, as opposed to sacrifice here anyway, but anyway been
willing to forgo her original lien.
Oh, so like she's מחילה, mechila, מחילה. mechila.
Yeah, Dove, you had a question? No? Okay. Yes.
So at some point, and maybe we're not at this point in
terms of the development of the כתובה, Ketubah,
didn't it originally let's say deposited at some earlier point, they got
married, whatever, as paid by the father? Yeah. And then didn't we
also say that then the groom would view that as a sunk
cost and then he'd be too, you know,
willing to divorce her? Right. I mean, so in which case then
we do it later, right?
In other words, he'd be too easy to divorce her.
That's what I mean. Yeah, I mean, let's say staying in the
marriage should be too easy to divorce her, you've already paid out
the כתובה. Ketubah. Right. So,
but we're not at this stage in the גמרא Gemara yet? In
other words, of course we are. Meaning it's payable to the father,
he didn't pay him anything then.
So that goes back to the earlier point, which is that, no,
this is totally at the final stage of the כתובה Ketubah where
it's payable at the end of the marriage and therefore it's a
brake against a too speedy divorce. Yeah, yeah, no, no, everything we
discussed before was like way back in ancient times. In the גמרא's
Gemara time, it's a normal כתובה Ketubah payable at the end and
therefore it's a brake to easy divorce. But the question still is,
how could we imagine paying the father if it's there also to
protect the girl? Okay, anyway, so what we have is we have
this interesting idea that the כתובה's Ketubah payable from the original time,
if she gets divorced at אירוסין Erusin it gets paid, and actually
it gets paid to the father. Okay, but then you have the
interesting thing that at the time of נישואין, Nisuin, when it gets
written, the obligation gets refreshed or redefined or somehow, and therefore according
to most חכמים, chachamim, you know, according to the חכמים, chachamim, then
it's payable to the girl. According to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda it
would depend whether she's still a קטנה ktana at that time, but
it gets
redefined, and then the question becomes, now that it's written and gets
redefined and a תוספת tosefet gets added, does the lien still exist
of the original stuff still exist even at the time of the
writing of the כתובה, Ketubah, and that's exactly the issue that the
גמרא Gemara is dealing with. Okay, so now let's take a look.
אמר מר. Amar Mar.
So now let's go back and look at what we said about
this 300 and the 200 כתובה, Ketubah, these competing כתובות. Ketubot. So
אי בעיא בהאי גוונא אי בעיא בהאי גוונא, i-ba'ei be-hai gavna i-ba'ei
be-hai gavna, so she wants to collect with this one or she
wants to collect with the other. לימא פליגא דרב נחמן, Leima pliga
de-Rav Nachman, let's say it argues on רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. דאמר
רב נחמן שני שטרות היוצאין זה אחר
זה. De-amar Rav Nachman shnei shetarot hayotzin zeh achar zeh. Okay, so
let's say you have two documents. Now they're not two IOUs, because
Michael could have borrowed 200 dollars from me today and 300 dollars
from me yesterday, or whatever, you know, you keep on borrowing more
money. But they are two documents of ownership, of transfer of property
of the same field. So Michael here comes with a document that
says that I sold him my co-op on
in 2012, and then he's got another document that says I sold
him my co-op in 2015. Okay, so when did I sell him
my co-op? 2012, 2015? Now what difference does it make? He owns
my co-op right now, it's already 2015.
So yes, but why, yeah, so that would matter for לקוחות lekuchot
against me, against you. Why does it matter to you? So right,
so if I sell it to Michael, right, people can, as we've
already discussed before, the
idea of lien, come, and I owe people
money, and they're going to say, "Well, I don't have any money,"
they're going to go take the co-op that Michael just bought from
me, and they'll take it away from Michael. Okay, great. So that
doesn't matter when I sold it to him. Either way, the לקוחות
lekuchot have rights to it based on their debit. Ah, but what
matters here is, is that either explicitly or implicitly, let's say implicitly
in a case of a sale, this is all debated, anyway, I'm
also have an obligation to Michael that if, if any creditor takes
the co-op away from him because of my debt, I will reimburse
him, okay, that I actually have that obligation to Michael. Michael's protected.
That's what Michael said. How's anybody protected if they buy anything? Right?
Some creditor might come and take it away. Well, maybe there's an
implicit insurance against that, and I will make it, make it good
to Michael. Okay, so now you realize what happens? Michael buys my
co-op from me, Michael now gets liens against my estate because if
creditors take it from Michael, he now has a right to collect
from me, and his liens on my estate to collect in that
case begin from the time I sold him the co-op. Is that
pretty clear? You guys got it? Okay. Because why didn't the creditors
take from, so it could be right, it could be, so it
could be that I went ahead and I sold my co-op to
Michael, then I sold my nice, you know, my house in Hawaii
to you, okay, and David comes to collect, and he... Michael, the
co-op is easier to take, so he's going to take the co-op
from Michael. Okay, but yeah I know, but he doesn't like the
hot weather, so then Michael is going to take the house in
Hawaii, you know what I'm saying? So it could be that either
way the creditors don't have the money to take from me. But
the fact that Michael has a lien allows, you know, access to
the property that I had sold you. But for two liens, all
I was saying was how do you get a third party somewhere?
No, no, it's so insurance, yeah, insurance was the wrong word. I
am providing the insurance. Okay, I am protecting Michael's estate, Michael's purchase.
But yeah, insurance was the wrong term to use. But I'm saying,
you're protecting me, but you might not have any assets to protect
me with. Yeah, I know, but that's all I can offer is
my own assets. So there's the risk. That's all I can offer
is my own assets. We don't have any third party providing the
insurance. So the question is when I sell my co-op here to
Michael, the date matters because he wants an earlier date because that
provides him earlier liens if he ever has to get reimbursed because
somebody has taken, you know, some creditor has gone to him. Okay,
but if he gave it back to me, what about back in
the interim? What if he sold it to me? Well, maybe, I
mean, okay, but there's no evidence of that, so we're not going
to assume that. So let's take a look. Okay, so here's the
question. שני שטרות היוצאים בזה אחר זה. Shnei Shtaros HaYotzim Bezeh Achar
Zeh. ביטל שני את הראשון. Bitel Sheni Es HaRishon. So Rav Nachman
says the second one supersedes the first, and therefore Michael's liens only
begin from the second date, which basically means for whatever reason, right,
because Michael didn't have to accept the second שטר. Shtar. I come
to Michael and say, Michael, here's a document that I sold my
co-op in 2015. He says, what are you talking about? I already
have the one from 2012. Somehow because he was willing to accept
the second one was showing that he was willing to forgo the
earlier lien. He was implicitly saying to me, we'll make it as
if
I only bought it from 2015. Okay, and he was willing to
forgo those earlier liens and the second one supersedes the first. Okay,
so that's what he says. So the גמרא Gemara says, well, we
don't say the same by the כתובות. Kesuvos. By the כתובות Kesuvos
we say you can choose which one you want to use. So
if Michael's got two שטרות, Shtaros, maybe he should be entitled to
choose which one to use. So let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says, so how does that... how does those fit with
one another? So the גמרא Gemara says, לאו מי איתמר עלה, Lav
Mi Itmar Alah, one minute, because it was said on it the
following thing. אמר רב פפא ומודי רב נחמן דאי הוסיף בה דקלא
לתוספת כתביה. Amar Rav Pappa U'Modei Rav Nachman De'ee Hosif Bah Dikla
Le'Tosefes Kasveih. No, it depends, does the second one give him any
benefit? Right? In the case of the 200 and 300, I could
say you get to choose. If you want to use the... if
you want to get a bigger amount, you'll have later liens, right?
So there's a tradeoff, you choose. So he says, if the second
document that I gave to Michael had an additional benefit. The second
document said not only did I sell you my co-op, I sold
you my parking space. No, even more, a parking space! I sold
you my parking space in the garage. So then we could say,
okay, I'm giving him a choice. You could either use the later
one with later liens but get the parking space, or use the
earlier one with earlier liens and not get the parking space. So
then you get to choose which one.
But if the second one...
a palm tree, okay, but if the second one
were the exact same terms of the first one, then the only...
then all I'm doing is superseding it, right? I'm saying that you
know, because it's a worse deal than the first one. It's the
same thing at a later time. So if Michael's accepting it and
I'm giving it to him, it must be saying we're agreeing that
he's forgoing the rights of the first one. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, ומודי רב נחמן דאי הוסיף בה דקלא לתוספת כתביה. U'Modei
Rav Nachman De'ee Hosif Bah Dikla Le'Tosefes Kasveih. If you add a
palm tree, for an additional amount... you gave it to him with
a later date but to give him the benefit of this additional
amount. הכא נמי הא הוסיף לה מידי. Hacha Nami Ha Hosif Lah
Midi. Here too, by the case of the 300, you add an
additional hundred and therefore... therefore that gives you the option.
So if you have
two different documents on the same thing, which one do you go
by? So if each one has a benefit... if the later one
has a benefit in terms of the amount or whatever, then it's
your choice which one to use. And I'm giving you the right
to pick which one to... you want you can use. If the
later one doesn't have a benefit and you were willing to accept
the later one, then basically you waive the rights of the earlier
one and the second one takes its place. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: גופא. Gufa. Let's go back and look
at the statement. אמר רב נחמן: Amar Rav Nachman: שני שטרות היוצאים
בזה אחר זה, Shnei Shtaros HaYotzim Bezeh Achar Zeh, two documents come
out on the same piece of property one after the other, ביטל
שני את הראשון, Bitel Sheni Es HaRishon, the second one superseded the
first as we said when there's no benefit to the second one.
So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר
רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa,
so we're repeating this and now we're just going to illustrate it
a little more, ומודי רב נחמן דאי הוסיף בה דקלא לתוספת כתביה,
U'Modei Rav Nachman De'ee Hosif Bah Dikla Le'Tosefes Kasveih, but if the
second one add an extra palm tree, then it was giving you
that extra benefit, so now it's sort of your choice which one
to
use. Okay. פשיטא, Pshita, the גמרא Gemara says, so now let's talk
about some illustrations or applications. It's obvious if ראשון במכר ושני במתנה.
Rishon Be'Mecher Ve'Sheni Be'Matanah. Let's say it wasn't an additional amount, okay,
an additional parking space or additional amount, but here's how they were
different. The first one said I sold him my co-op, and the
second one said I gave him my co-op. it's a gift. So
is there some benefit of having it framed as a gift rather
than a sale? So the answer is yes, ליפוי כוחו הוא דכתב
ליה. le-yafei kocho hu de-ktav leih.
There's a benefit of using the later one as a gift because
it gives you more strength. What more strength does it give Michael?
משום דינא דבר מצרא. mishum dina de-bar metzra. Okay,
because of the rule of the neighbor. What's the rule of the
neighbor? There's a rule of a neighbor that if I sell Michael
here my co-op, then Dov, who's got the co-op right next door
to mine or right under mine, can say, one minute, I have
first right of refusal, because if you sell me your co-op, I
can break through the wall and I can have a nice big
expanded co-op, right, or break through the floor and have a and
have a duplex. Okay, and actually the דינא דבר מצרא dina de-bar
metzra means that I'm not allowed under certain circumstances to sell to
a stranger before I give my neighbor the first right of refusal.
It's just like, you know, like modern...
what, they break through the walls and they make... but modern הלכה,
halacha, I don't know how much people פוסק pasken by modern הלכה.
halacha. I know it's a big deal.
I can tell you that Heschel School board applied this הלכה, halacha,
yeah, for selling its 89th Street building to B'nai Jeshurun on 88th.
They
gave them the first right of refusal?
Yes, because they had originally owned the building in 1920.
Wow, fascinating.
And they were neighbors, and and they gave a certain amount of
time, they raised the money, and it went to B'nai Jeshurun. Wow,
fascinating.
פשיטא. pshita. Okay, there you go. Great, great. So there, so there,
it was actually applied in principle. Excellent. So, so therefore, but interestingly,
if I that's only if I'm doing it to make money. Then
you could say, hey, if you can make just as much money
by selling it to your neighbor, then you have a responsibility to
sell to your neighbor, not to sell it to some stranger. Okay,
you could demand the same price, but you have a responsibility to
offer to your neighbor first. But if I'm giving it as a
gift, you can't tell me, oh, don't give it as a gift
to your best friend, give it as a gift to your neighbor.
I have a right to give a gift to whoever I want
to. So if I write the second document to Michael as a
gift, then that is giving him the ability to protect himself against
the דינא דבר מצרא, dina de-bar metzra, against the neighbor's claim. Okay,
so then we would say that then it's Michael, you get to
choose. You can use the first one with earlier liens, or you
can use the second one, which doesn't maybe has no liens, right?
There's a whole question maybe a gift has no liens, because Michael
didn't put out any money. Okay, so you can either use the
earlier one with liens and with an early date, or you can
use the later one with no liens but protect you against דינא
דבר מצרא. dina de-bar metzra. You choose, and that's how we'll interpret
it. Not that one negated the other, but he has a choice,
each one has their own benefit. Okay, so because of דינא דבר
מצרא. dina de-bar metzra. וכל שכן, ve-chol she-ken, and certainly we would
say, if you did the reverse, ראשון בממתנה ושני במכר, rishon be-matana
ve-sheni be-mecher, if the first one was a gift and the second
one was document was written as a sale, that Michael also has
the choice which one to use. Why? How's the second one better?
It's got a later date. דאמרינן משום דינא דבר חובא דכתב הכי
de-amrinan mishum dina de-bar chova de-ktav hachi because the second one, if
I if if it's written as a sale and then a creditor
comes and takes it away from Michael, then he can get reimbursed
and come back to me. If I give him a gift, right,
he can't come back and demand be reimbursed, be reimbursed, Michael, it
was a gift, like you know, okay. But if it was a
sale and he put out money, he can. So if the earlier
one was a gift and the second one was a sale, then
there's a benefit for it being framed as a sale. The benefit
is, although it has a later date, it entitles him to be
reimbursed if somebody comes and collects it. So the idea is that
if each document is, you know, if the later document, which is
worse in terms of a later date, is better in some way,
then it's Michael's choice and we don't say it supersedes the previous
one. And it could be and whether the order is מכר מתנה
mecher matana or מתנה ומכר, matana u-mecher, there will always be some
benefit in those certain benefits that come through one over the other.
In other words, okay, I understand if you're מוסיף אדקלא, mosif adikla,
okay, you've changed something. But if you do a ראשון במכר ושני
במתנה, rishon be-mecher ve-sheni be-matana, you've already sold it. So like, how
am I protected against the בר מצרא? bar metzra? It's not yours
to give to him as a gift. So that's the... right. So
so thank you for pointing that out. Look, the point is is
that I the second one is a fiction. Once I sold it
to you, I did not resell it to you at the later
date. Once I sold it to you in 2012, I did not
give it to you as a gift in 2015. But the second
one is basically, since we're both agreeing to it, we're allowed to
create that as a fiction, which is pretty interesting because like the,
you know, the neighbors lose out, right? So you know, so why
are we... but I guess the but the point is is that
in theory it's all ממון, mamon, in theory you could have given
it back to me and then I could give it back to
you, so we're allowed to create this fiction as well as if
I gave it to you as a gift since both of us
agree. And if we wanted to, we could create that reality. Okay,
so but you are right, it's not like we're actually claiming the
second thing is what happened.
We're allowing it to present it as if it was the second
thing that happened. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, אלא אישתכח
בנכסי. ela ishtachach be-nichsei. but if they are both done as bills
of sale or both done as a writ of a gift and
without any additional property being mentioned, then the second one is only
detrimental, and since Michael agreed to accept this, ביטול
שני את הראשון, bitul sheni es harishon, the second one supersedes the
first one. מאי טעמא, Mai ta’ama, now what's the mechanism through which
this works that the second one supersedes? רב פפא אמר אימר אודויי
אודי ליה. Rav Papa amar eimar oduye odi leh. So it's implicitly
like Michael is admitting by the fact that he's accepting one of
a later date of 2015, he's saying I'm merely admitting that really
it was only sold to me in 2015, not in 2012, which
is funny, again, because it's not really what happened, but it's like
הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים דמי. hoda’as ba’al din k’me’ah edim dami.
It's implicitly read as if you admit, yeah, the 2012 thing never
happened, we made a mistake, or whatever, even if it's not factually
true, it's treated as an admission that it only really happened by
the later date. Okay. Even if there's witnesses being in there? Yes.
signatures? Doesn't matter, הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים דמי hoda’as ba’al din
k’me’ah edim dami creates its own legal fiction even if we know
it didn't actually happen. Okay. רב אחא אמר אימר אחולי אחליה לשיעבודיה.
Rav Acha amar eimar acholi achleh l’shibudeh. We don't have to go
that far. What Michael is basically saying is that he is foregoing
his liens from 2012. Of course you sold them to me in
2012, but implicitly that I'm going to accept the document of 2015
means that I waive the liens I have against you that began
in 2012. Okay, so what's so there's a big נפקא מינה, nafka
mina, because one makes it as if the whole thing only happened
in 2015, the other thing only is a נפקא מינה nafka mina
only says that you give up your rights to the liens. So
let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says מאי בינייהו, mai
beinaihu, what's the difference? איכא בינייהו אירעואי סהדי ולשלומי פירי ולארנונא. Ika
beinaihu iru’ei sahadei u’lishlumei peiri u’ltaxsa. So אירעואי סהדי iru’ei sahadei is
a is a says that if Michael says it never really happened
implicitly, so this becomes the question how far do you take the
legal fiction? So if it never happened, the 2012, but we have
witnesses that signed the 2012 document, so by saying it never happened,
he basically has invalidated those witnesses. Now תוספות Tosfos comes yells and
says, "What the heck do you mean? Since when does Michael have
the power to invalidate witnesses? It's just a complete fiction that we're
pretending as if it didn't happen, but how can you go ahead
and impugn the integrity of these witnesses?" So what תוספות Tosfos says
it means is, it means that it would affect other documents that
Michael has with the same witnesses on it. Meaning not in general,
in general of course we believe those witnesses, but in addition to
having the שטר shtar that I went ahead and sold him my
house and that's signed here by Dov and David, there's also a
שטר shtar that he has that that that John sold him his
car, you know, at a certain date and also signed by Dov
and David. So once he concedes to me that the 2012 document
is invalid and it never really happened and he's implicitly saying the
witnesses were false, he's also given up his rights to the other
שטר shtar he has with also the same witnesses on it, because
you have to be consistent within your legal fictions. Okay, which is
still pretty crazy, right? I mean to I mean even though it
didn't happen, they didn't say that... Right, but implicitly by saying that
the 2012 document didn't happen, you're saying that they were false witnesses.
So at least vis-a-vis you and your rights, they're false witnesses. So
any other document you have with those signatures, you're also invalidating. So
it's shifting the application from the integrity of the witnesses to the
legal כח koach of the documents with those signatures on it. But
again, it's a little crazy. You've got to be you've got to
be really careful before you accept a second document. But it's only
vis-a-vis me, but I don't have any power to invalidate anyone else.
Right, anyone else, right. Now that's one, that's bad I mean that's
like I mean way out of proportion I think of what we
would imagine. But let's just do the other נפקא מינה. nafka mina.
לשלומי פירי Lishlumei peiri is eas- is easier. If Mich- no, no,
taxes ארנונא arnona is going to be the third one. Michael has
been eating the fruit for the last three years. If he's basically
saying okay I waive the liens, fine, you waive the liens, you're
still entitled to the fruit. You've been living in my כח. koach.
You're entitled to. Okay, you just lose any you're just waiving the
liens. But if you say it never really happened in 2012, I'll
say, "Oh, it didn't happen? Back rent, Michael. Three years back rent.
Okay, pay me all the fruit that you've been eating." And the
third נפקא מינה nafka mina is taxes. Okay, which is, here's the
one thing you benefit from. Okay, I'll pay you the back rent,
but you've got to pay the back taxes. Okay, because you know,
because if I haven't owned it in the last three years, if
Michael says he hasn't owned it and I'm the one that's owned
it in the last three years, then I'm the one that has
to be paying the the property taxes for those years as opposed
to if he did own it and he just waived the liens.
Obviously the the much less radical thing to say, we would want
to interpret it, I would assume, in the narrowest way, you know,
and the narrowest way to interp- and the way that's also most
true to the facts. And therefore what we would probably want to
say is the position that he waived the liens. It's pretty radical
what the implications would be if we'd say that he basically he
didn't own it in the last three years. So let's just finish
and then I'll take your question, David. So מה הוי עלה דכתובה,
Mah havei ala d'kesuvah, what was the upshot of the whole כתובה
kesuvah question, which is when it's written at the time of the
נישואין, nisuin, do the liens do you lose the earlier lien? So
that was the first position we had, that the earlier liens continue
after the writing of the כתובה, Kesuvah, the 100 and 200 liens.
The new additions start now. וחכמים אומרים אחד זה ואחד זה מן
הנישואין. V'chamim Omrim Echad Zeh V'echad Zeh Min Ha'nisuin. And the חכמים
Chamim say no, that after the writing of the כתובה Kesuvah all
the liens are start, you know, everything starts fresh and therefore none
of the old liens survive and the new debt that's at the
time of the writing of the כתובה, Kesuvah, all the liens are
focused on that moment. והלכה היא אחד זה ואחד זה מן הנישואין.
V'halacha Hi Echad Zeh V'echad Zeh Min Ha'nisuin. And that's the way
we rule, that at least by the כתובה Kesuvah case, the old
liens do not survive and whatever obligations existed at the time of
אירוסין Erusin do not continue at the time of נישואין. Nisuin. David,
you had a question. Yeah, if there are these two documents, what
makes the witnesses' signature on one any more valid than the witnesses'
signature on the other? Nothing, but if Michael chooses to use the
later one, right? So they have the same, two documents and they
might be, oh, you're saying let's say they're all the same witnesses?
No, okay, that would be interesting, that could have been another נפקא
מינה. Nafka Mina. No, so that's the point. We're not believing him.
What he says has absolutely no implication in anybody else in the
world using these witnesses, but he is saying something and he's hurting
his own interest by pre- if it's, yeah, but it's איסור. Issur.
It's more like הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים
דמי.
Hoda'as Ba'al Din
K'mea Edim Dami.
So he comes and he says I'm using the second document.
You are, and we know you've got an earlier one
with other witnesses on it. You are basically telling the court that
as far as your interests are concerned, you treat the early witnesses
as false witnesses. And therefore, we're going to be consistent with that
and apply it to all documents you have with those witnesses on
it. But you, you have, I don't care about what, you're only
making a claim about yourself, right? Not about other people. Yeah, I
follow that. I'm just saying this is some, it's a bit weird,
pardon me. Yeah, it's totally weird. Because in other words, if he's
saying there are two sets of witnesses and he's calling those false,
then maybe these are false. No, because you chose to use, you
chose to use the second one. So since you're choosing to use
the second one, you're implicitly invalidating the first one, right? But again,
it's not some objective statement if you have two sets, one of
them are false. No, we're not saying that. You know, your choice
to use one is implicitly interpreted as a statement that the other
ones are invalid. Okay. Now we get, now we have a major
shift. I don't know how major any of these shifts are, but
you know, it's interesting to the degree to which our משניות Mishnayot
are tracking cases in the תורה Torah that deal with young girls
and young girls around כתובה Kesuvah related issues, right? So one case
of course is the cases of אונס Ones and מפתה Mefateh where
the whole payment of the 50 שקל Shekel is the basis for
the כתובה Kesuvah and, you know, as we've discussed earlier, the whole
idea of the מוהר. Mohar. I mean, the 50, the payment of
the קנס Knas of the 50 שקל Shekel reflects a societal reality
of מוהר. Mohar. And that societal reality, right, of a bride price,
and that societal reality of מוהר Mohar becomes the, becomes the basis
for the eventual Rabbinic institution of כתובה. Kesuvah. So we've been talking
about the case of אונס Ones and מפתה, Mefateh, which is a
case about a young girl and about the כתובה Kesuvah related type
of a payment, the קנס Knas which is about
the מוהר Mohar which is about the כתובה. Kesuvah. And now we're
switching to
the other case
in the תורה, Torah,
which is about a כתובה Kesuvah type of a related payment, which
is, or about an, a case about the after the wedding night,
which is the מוציא שם רע. Motzi Shem Ra. Right? The guy
comes and he claims after the wedding night, the girl, my wife
wasn't a virgin, and therefore he suspects that she's committed adultery. So
what does the תורה Torah say happens? If she actually is, evidence
that she has committed adultery, she gets executed. If there is not
evidence, if it, if it turns out that he's lying, okay, and
we'll have to, now how do you prove that he's lying? Do
you know how much he pays, Michael? מאה כסף. Me'ah Kesef. What's
מאה כסף? Me'ah Kesef? Two times the חמישים כסף, Chamishim Kesef, right?
So when we're dealing with אונס Ones and מפתה, Mefateh, we were
dealing with a fine of חמישים כסף, Chamishim Kesef, which is 200
זוז. Zuz. He gets a, basically a fine of כפל. Kefel. You
were, and now of course he was trying to kill her. Okay,
so fine. Instead of killing her, we don't kill you, we give
you lashes. Okay, but you were also trying to rob her of
her כתובה, Kesuvah, so instead, so now you have to pay double.
You have to pay not the חמישים כסף Chamishim Kesef of the
כתובה, Kesuvah, you have to pay double. So you have to appreciate
that all of these are in the constellation of, right, the girl
and the כתובה Kesuvah and after the wedding night and so on,
which of course gets us back to the first פרק. Perek. Because
the first פרק Perek is get married on a Wednesday, so if
you find out that your wife isn't a virgin, you come to
the בית דין Beis Din the next morning and you deal with
that whole court case. Well, that's exactly leading into this case in
the תורה Torah about the מוציא שם רע. Motzi Shem Ra. Okay.
So here's where we actually turn to מוציא שם רע Motzi Shem
Ra in the משנה. Mishna. Could we also say they only stay
married because you're going to get to it, but you know, both
he, she have to agree to this like to stay together? Uh,
yeah, so we'll see. הגיורת שנתגיירה. Hagiores Shenisgayera. Now, of course, the
משנה, Mishnah, rather than just doing a nice introduction like I just
did or starting with the actual פסוקים Pesukim in the תורה Torah
and talking about here's the story of מוציא שם רע, Motzi Shem
Ra, talks about a possible you know strange case or an exception.
Okay, so הגיורת שנתגיירה בתה עמה. Hagiyores she'nisgayra bita ima. So a
convert woman converted with her daughter. וזנתה. Vizanta. And then the daughter
had committed adultery and she was married you know she was a
נערה Na'arah that was married to a נערה מאורסה Na'arah Me'orasah to
a man and she committed adultery. So it's death penalty, הרי זו
בחנק. Harei zo bichenek. Now the חידוש Chiddush there is that the
תורה Torah normally says that a נערה מאורסה Na'arah Me'orasah that commits
adultery gets stoned, right? And that's also in the פרשה Parsha of
מוציא שם רע. Motzi Shem Ra. But she, while it's adultery and
it's a capital crime, does not get stoned. You know why? Because
the תורה Torah describes the case, no. So you could say because
she's not a בתולה, betulah, but רש"י Rashi says it could even
be that the daughter converted under three. But because the תורה Torah
describes the case as you take her to פתח בית אביה, Petach
Beis Aviha, you take her to the opening of the father's house
and you stone her. So in a case where she is converted
and she does not have a legal father, she's excluded from the
punishment of the stoning. She's still adultery, but she's excluded from the
special פרשה Parsha of נערה מאורסה, Na'arah Me'orasah, okay, which is partly
the מוציא שם רע Motzi Shem Ra פרשה Parsha and partly the
stoning פרשה. Parsha. אין לה לא פתח בית אב, Ein la lo
petach beis av, now she, now spelling it out. So also if
she committed adultery, this woman who does not have a legal father—not
only her father's dead, she doesn't have a legal father at all—so
you would not take her to the father's house, you know, in
order to do the whole ritual of the execution, you would not
bring her to the father's house. ולא מאה סלע, Velo Me'ah Sela,
and you would not have the fine of the מוציא שם רע
Motzi Shem Ra of the hundred סלע. sela. So she basically would
not, you would not apply the principles of the special category of
מוציא שם רע.
Motzi Shem Ra. The same way had she
let's say not been a virgin or let's say she had not
been a נערה, Na'arah, let's say she had been a בוגרת. Bogeres.
Okay, so the special categories of the תורה's Torah case of מוציא
שם רע Motzi Shem Ra is number one, if she committed adultery
it's stoning, it's not חנק. Chenek. That special case number one and
again just like the case of אונס ומפתה, Ones u'Mefateh, this applies
only to a נערה Na'arah who is a whatever, a בתולה. besulah.
Okay, everybody with me? So we haven't spelled it out, but again
it's the case that she's not a בוגרת, Bogeres, she's a בתולה.
besulah. So what is special about it? If you have those things
and the guy was being מוציא שם רע Motzi Shem Ra whatever,
so
anyway so number one is, or whatever, she commits adultery, you have
סקילה, Sekilah, okay, and number two is if he's lying you have
the whole, you have the fine of the hundred, you have the
fine of the hundred כסף, Kesef, excuse me. So in this case
where she
doesn't have a legal father, all you have is a simple case
of adultery.
You don't have the special case of נערה מאורסה Na'arah Me'orasah so
there's not going to be any פתח בית אב, Petach Beis Av,
there's not going to be any hundred זוז. zuz. I keep on
saying hundred זוז, zuz, כסף, Kesef, excuse me, four hundred זוז. zuz.
Yes, also. Okay, and we'll see about that. Correct. היתה הורתה שלא
בקדושה ולידתה בקדושה.
Haiseh horasa shelo
bikedusha v'lidasah bikedusha.
Let's say she was conceived when her mother was not Jewish and
then her mother converted while she was pregnant with her and then
she was born when she was Jewish. In this case, הרי זו
בסקילה, harezo bisekilah, interesting, because she is a born Jew she gets
the סקילה, Sekilah, because the גמרא's Gemara going to say one of
the exclusions here is not just the אב Av idea but it's
כי עשתה נבלה בישראל. ki asa nevala b'Yisrael. So therefore being a
born Jew even without any legal father is enough to get you
into the special category of סקילה Sekilah rather than חנק. Chenek. Okay,
but ואין לה לא פתח בית אב ולא מאה סלע. v'ein la
lo petach beis av velo me'ah sela. Because there's no legal father,
not only is the father dead there was never a legal father,
there's not going to be the special idea of taking her to
the door of the father's house as the process of סקילה Sekilah
and there's not going to be the special idea of the hundred
סלע. sela. I keep on saying hundred סלע, sela, כסף, Kesef, excuse
me, four hundred זוז. zuz. Yes. He would? Well no no no,
excuse me, he wouldn't. I mean we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara,
but the reality is the only הלכה Halacha she gets here is
the סקילה Sekilah הלכה. Halacha. Okay, היתה הורתה ולידתה בקדושה haiseh horasa
velidasa bikedusha if basically her mother was a convert but she was
both conceived and born after her mother had converted. הרי היא כבת
ישראל לכל דבריה, Harei hi kevas Yisrael l'chol devareha, and she has
the normal הלכה Halacha and now finally we start with the normal
הלכה. Halacha. יש לה אב. Yesh la av. And I'm sorry now,
יש לה אב ואין לה פתח בית אב yesh la av v'ein
la petach beis av let's say a normal girl, whatever, she's got
her father but her father doesn't own a house, they're homeless or
they've got I don't know they've got a tent or something they're
gypsy or she's rental maybe or יש לה פתח בית אב yesh
la petach beis av or no there is a father's house and
a doorway ואין לה אב v'ein la av but her father is
dead so it's not a case that she's a convert she had
a legal father her father's dead. father's just she's an orphan. הרי
זה בסקילה, harei zeh biskila, then she also gets סקילה. skila. Now
it doesn't tell you what about the hundred זוז zuz and about
the and the פתח petach you know and so on. That's that's
not clear, but it says הרי זו בסקילה, harei zo biskila, which
is not such a חידוש chiddush because we already know that the
woman who was born, you know, who was conceived as a non-Jew
and born as a Jew who doesn't, who never had a father,
gets סקילה. skila. לא נאמר פתח בית אב אלא למצוה. lo ne'emar
petach beit av ela l'mitzvah. The need to have the father's house
is only for a מצוה. mitzvah. So basically this was not clear
because it did not have the final case we wanted to know
which was the hundred זוז. zuz. Okay, so does everybody, I get
this, it was not the most clearly written משנה. mishnah. Basically the
תורה Torah talks about a case about a what, yeah, well let's
just נערה בתולה מאורסה לאיש. na'arah betulah me'orasah l'ish. Okay, so you've
got נערה na'arah and בתולה, betulah, these are things we've seen before,
that's taken for granted. Okay, what's different here is that she's a
מאורסה, me'orasah, that she's a married woman. And then the case is
that the husband claims לא נמצאו בתולים לנערה, lo nimtze'u betulim l'na'arah,
right? לא נמצאו בתולים לנערה. lo nimtze'u betulim l'na'arah. If she's מאורסה,
me'orasah, she's נשואה? nesu'ah? This is the case... no, because he claims
that she had sex before the נישואין, nisu'in, right? So לא נמצאו
בתולים לנערה, lo nimtze'u betulim l'na'arah, so אם אמת היה, im emet
hayah, אם אמת היה הדבר הזה, im emet hayah hadavar hazeh, לא
נמצאו בתולים לנערה, lo nimtze'u betulim l'na'arah, so אם אמת, im emet,
so then what does it say? והוציאו את הנערה אל פתח בית
אביה וסקלוה. vehotzi'u et hana'arah el petach beit aviha uskeluha. Okay, so
כי עשתה נבלה בישראל. ki astah nevalah b'Yisrael. So you have פתח
בית אביה, petach beit aviha, that's particularly like part of the ritual
and סקילה skila as opposed to חנק. chenek. So a normal woman
who commits adultery is חנק, chenek, a נערה בתולה na'arah betulah who
committed adultery as an ארוסה arusah gets סקילה. skila. It's considered worse.
Exactly, she's younger, she's still in her father's house. Exactly. Okay, so
that's one aspect of when you have these conditions met, פתח בית
אביה וסקלוה. petach beit aviha uskeluha. Now if she's not אמת, emet,
then what does it say? How does it introduce not אמת? emet?
Well, actually the אם אמת im emet was the second part. He
introduces it by saying if it if it is, right, then... meaning
if he was telling, you know, the lie. If he lied. ויסרו
אותו מאה כסף. veyisru oto me'ah kesef. Okay, so וענשו אותו. ve'anshu
oto. Well, first actually והחזיקו את האיש ויסרו אותו. vehecheziku et ha'ish
veyisru oto. Okay, right. ויסרו אותו, veyisru oto, which is מלקות. malkus.
Okay, so here he's lying. מלקות, malkus, וענשו אותו מאה כסף, ve'anshu
oto me'ah kesef, which is ונתנו לאבי הנערה. venatnu l'avi hana'arah. Right,
so this is... ולא תהיה לאישה. velo tihyeh l'ishah. Right, fine, we'll
deal about that later. Okay, so מאה כסף me'ah kesef as I
said, that's double, right, that's double the...
so here he was trying to kill her so he gets מלקות,
malkus, I don't know why he doesn't get killed, okay, because it's
not עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, and he was trying to make her
lose her כתובה, kesuvah, which was with 50 כסף, kesef, he pays
double, he pays מאה כסף.
me'ah kesef. Now all of these special הלכות, halachos, this is מוציא
שם רע, motzi shem ra, okay, because he's found to be a
liar and this is מוציא שם רע motzi shem ra but he's
telling the truth. So this is a called... this is the case
this is called נערה מאורסה. na'arah me'orasah. Okay, if these are like
the
halachic frames for this.
This is a betrothed woman commits adultery, it's סקילה. skila. He's lying
about it, he
gets מלקות malkus and מאה כסף. me'ah kesef.
So the question is what the משנה mishnah is dealing with is
let's say she doesn't... now here it says כי עשתה נבלה בישראל.
ki astah nevalah b'Yisrael. So we have a couple of things going
on here. So we have בישראל b'Yisrael as another criteria. So what
the משנה mishnah is saying is if she was not Jewish and
converted, or even הורתה בקדושה ולידתה שלא
בקדושה,
horatah bikdushah
velidatah shelo bikdushah, etc. So... I'm sorry, if she was not Jewish
and converted, so she started her life as not a ישראל, Yisrael,
right? So then if she's not a ישראל, Yisrael, she started her
life that way, none of these things apply. So she would get
חנק, chenek, no מאה כסף, me'ah kesef, etc. Wait, am I saying
this wrong? She becomes a ישראל Yisrael and then she does that.
Right. Now, I understand. But somehow this is used to say she's
out of the whole category, out of all the special הלכות. halachos.
If however she was born as Jewish, but she was conceived as
not Jewish so the case has no legal father, so she has
no legal father so she still gets סקילה. skila. Even though she
doesn't have פתח בית אב, petach beit av, she still gets סקילה,
skila, okay? But wait, is there a way to like write it
in there like which is which? Like, you know, because we have
a whole bunch of permutations. So I'm trying to think it well,
I'm trying to think about it. So okay, so בישראל b'Yisrael means
okay, if she was born not Jewish
then all bets are off, then nothing,
no special, you know, no special laws. Okay, so she gets חנק,
chenek, no מאה כסף, me'ah kesef, etc. Here we said פתח בית
אב, petach beit av, so if she has...
no legal father and what's the case?
Then then she get then, right, if she has no legal father,
that's the second case, then interestingly, we say this is only למצוה.
limitzvah. So right, end of the mishnah says פתח בית אב petach
beis av is only למצוה.
limitzvah. So no legal father, she still gets סקילה. skilah. Okay, but
not not with the טכס tekes so to speak, not with not
בפתח בית אביה. bepetach beis avi'ah. Right? Okay, but that's the second
case of the mishnah. She has no legal father, so she gets
סקילה. skilah. But she does not have, right the מאה כסף. me'ah
kesef. So this is interesting. If she's got no legal father, she
has סקילה, skilah, but not, I mean, I don't know again, there's
not a good visual, I haven't figured out a good visual way
to do this. But anyway, she does סקילה, skilah, but no מאה
כסף. me'ah kesef. And that's interesting, like why not? Here it says
אביה avi'ah and וסקלוה uskaluha and we still give her סקילה, skilah,
right? So why she doesn't get the מאה כסף me'ah kesef here?
I mean, it does say ונתנו לאבי הנערה. venasnu la'avi hana'arah. It
says only if she, if only if he's lying. Yeah, I know,
but we're saying if he is lying, if he is lying. Okay,
so this is scenario number one. If she's not Jewish, no special
laws. Right? The special laws are סקילה, skilah, בית אב, beis av,
and if he's lying, it's מאה כסף. me'ah kesef. Okay, so here
if she's born not Jewish, no special laws, not סקילה, skilah, not
מאה כסף. me'ah kesef. If she has no legal father, right, then
she yes gets the סקילה, skilah, but no the מאה כסף. me'ah
kesef. Now, that's strange. Here it says פתח בית אב petach beis
av and we're still giving her the סקילה, skilah, but we're not
going to do in this scenario the מאה כסף, me'ah kesef, maybe
because it says ונתנו לאבי הנערה. venasnu la'avi hana'arah. Okay? And the
end case of the mishnah was that if basically not only she
has no legal father, but her father is dead, she's an orphan,
it also says we're still going to give סקילה. skilah. What it
doesn't tell us is, will, if she's an orphan, will there be
a payment of the מאה כסף? me'ah kesef? Okay, that's not clear
in the mishnah, and that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to
deal with then also then, if she's born no father whatever. So
no legal father, now the question is if she's an orphan, okay,
then it also says yes סקילה, skilah, but מאה כסף, me'ah kesef,
that's going to be the question. We don't know the answer about
the מאה כסף, me'ah kesef, and that's what we're going to discuss
tomorrow. And also and also about the ולא תהיה לאשה velo tihyeh
le'ishah like. Yeah, okay, that also, but let's at least first just
focus on this. Okay? All right, we continue tomorrow. Yeah, and he
has to stay with her for the rest of his life? Yes.
So she has, does she have? Yeah, that's what Michael was asking.
Yes, yes. Can she, can she...